

VIJAY KUMAR SINGH

- ▼ Kolkata,India,711101
- 9831865274
- singh.vijay77@hotmail.com

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

A highly motivated specialized IT Infrastructure Professional with 20 yrs of experience in Enterprise Architect, Technical Advisory, Data Centre Modernization, IT Operation Management, Information Security, Information Audit, Business Continuity as per Financial Industry Standards, and Program & Project Management in large geographical distributed organization with over 250+ Remotes Sites and 10000+ End Users. Played a vital role in designing the Hybrid cloud (On-premise, Azure & AWS) approach, played a crucial role in creating Landing zone architecture for AWS and implemented the same. Expertise in migration of Legacy Applications to Next Generation Systems with new-age digital transformation spanning, inception, engineering, development, delivery, and support

EXPERIENCE

GM - EUC LEAD, 04/2021 - Current

Poonawalla Fincorp Limited, Kolkata, India

- Lead a team of 50+ IT Professionals in providing support for business applications,
 Delivery, Network Infrastructure, Branch IT Operation and Infrastructure Projects for Poonawalla Group
- Setting up Process and Strategizing action plan for Improvement in IT Services
- Tracked expenses in EUC Assets and implemented cost controls to eliminate overages.
- Managing Complete EUC IT Asset Life Cycle Management.
- Collaborated with line managers on department performance and KPIs
- Acquisition and Implementation of New IT Solutions For Business's Competitive Advantage
- Prepared reports and correspondence on complex resource management issues.

GENERAL MANAGER-IT INFRA, 04/2019 - 03/2021

Magma Fincorp Ltd, Kolkata, India

- Planning & Implementation of New DC on Virtual Technology and Backup Procedures
- IT Project , Infrastructure and Delivery Management
- Defining Process and Procedures for Support and SLA
- Assist in Creating IT & Security Policy including its implementation, meeting compliance by auditing
- Application Helpdesk & IT Service Desk Management
- Empowered staff members to contribute to continuous improvement, quality and growth of company.
- New Branch Role Out Across the Country. Tablet & BTP Rolled out for FOSs
- Preparing and Presenting Weekly, Monthly & Quarterly Report

SENIOR MANAGER-IT, 04/2017 - 03/2019

Magma Fincorp Ltd, Kolkata, India

- Accountable for Co-hosted Data Centre Operation @ Hyderabad
- Data Centre having having 70+ Physical & 300+ VM Servers, 4 Storage built on Virtualization Technology using VMware, Hyper-V and OVM
- Perform troubleshoot on Data Centre, identify issues and assist in timely resolution of same
- Responsible for New IT Infrastructure Deployments and Management
- Monitor all activities related to analysis and implement all Data Centre plans
- Coordinate with various departments and perform integration of critical systems into infrastructure
- Coordinate with IT and business teams and develop strategies to ensure achievement of **Data Centre Capacity**

MANAGER - IT, 04/2015 - 03/2017

Magma Fincorp Ltd, Kolkata

- Accountable for Migration of Data Centre from STT Global -Kolkata to STT Global -Hyderabad and implementation of Hypervisor Technology
- Capacity Planning and Removal of Legacy Physical Servers
- Successfully deployed vSphere and vCenter Infrastructure in New Data Centre
- Successfully migrated Services from Physical Server to Virtual Servers with minimal Downtime
- Successfully deployment of Air-Watch MDM Solution for 5K FOSs with AD Integration Including MEM (Mobile Email Management)
- Application Helpdesk & IT Service Desk Management

OTHER ENGAGEMENTS

- Deputy Manager IT (April-2014 to March-2015) in Magma Fincorp Ltd.
- Asst. Manager IT (April-2010 to March-2014) in Magma Fincorp Ltd
- Senior Executive IT (April-2007 to March-2010) in Magma Shrachi Finance Ltd
- Executive IT (May-2005 to March-2007) in Magma Leasing Ltd
- Resident Engineer (Nov-2004 to Apr-2005) in C-DAC (Client Intellectual Property of India)
- Customer Support Executive (Jun-2002 to Nov-2004) in Ontrack Systems Ltd
- Office Automation Executive (Jun-2000 to Oct-2001) in Computer Media, Macheda
- Private Tutor (Sub: PCM & Std: 9th & 10th)

CORE QUALIFICATIONS

- Core Competencies Includes Solution Architecture/Design
- Execution of IT Roadmaps & Budgets to achieve objectives
- Data Center Operation & Service Desk Management
- Business Process Improvement
- Team Leadership
- Coaching & Mentoring

EDUCATION

Calcutta University, Kolkata, WB, 1998

B. Sc: PCM

IIHT, Kolkata, 2002

Diploma in Computer Hardware Engineering: Computer Hardwarer
IIHT, Kolkata, 2003 Certificate Course in Windows 2003 Network Administration: Windows Server
HP Education, Kolkata, 2007 Certificate Course in Virtualization Server Environment: Virtualization
Trend Micro, New Delhi, DL, 2008 Successfully Completed Corporate Training in Trend Micro Security Suites 2.0: EDRO
VMware, Bangalore, 2012 Certificate Course in VCP - VMware Certified Professional: Virtualization
VMware, Bangalore, 2015 Certificate Course in Air-Watch Mobility (Configure & Deploy): Mobile Device Management
Simplilearn, Bangalore, 2020 Certificate Course in ITIL4.0 Foundation Course: Process

PERSONAL DETAILS

- Date of Birth: 20-Jun-1977
- Permanent Address: Flat # 202, Block B, Sangam Apartment, 42, Bon Behari Bose Road, Howrah - 711101
- Nationality: Indian
- Language Known: English, Hindi, Bengali